Hello, English learners.
你好，英语学习者。
Welcome back to another lesson here with us at EnglishPod.
欢迎回到 EnglishPod 的另一节课。
My name is Marco.
我是 Marco。
And I'm Erica.
我是 Erica。
And today we are going to have a very casual, normal conversation.
今天我们要进行一次非常随意、正常的对话。
That's right.
没错。
We're going to listen in on some small talk between a taxi driver and the passenger.
我们将听一段出租车司机和乘客之间的闲聊。
Small talk.
闲聊。
So that's basically...
所以这基本上就是……
Mm, small, short conversations you have with someone that you don't know very well.
嗯，就是你和不太熟悉的人进行的简短对话。
Okay.
好的。
And you can ask them simple questions like how old are you, where you're from, etc.
你可以问他们简单的问题，比如你多大了、你从哪里来等等。
That's right.
没错。
And this can be really hard for English learners because they often don't know what the right
这对英语学习者来说可能很难，因为他们常常不知道什么该说，
thing to say or the right thing to talk about.
或者该聊什么话题。
So we're going to give you a lot of phrases in this lesson that you can use in small talk.
所以这节课我们会给你很多可以在闲聊中使用的短语。
Okay.
好的。
So we don't have anything to preview today.
今天我们没有什么需要预习的内容。
So let's listen to the dialogue for the first time and then we'll come back.
那么我们先听一遍对话，然后再回来。
Where to, miss?
小姐，去哪儿？
Hi.
嗨。
Crenshaw and Hawthorne at the Holiday Inn that is on that corner.
去那个拐角处的假日酒店，在克伦肖和霍桑街。
Sure thing.
没问题。
So where are you flying in from?
你从哪儿飞来的？
From China.
从中国。
Really?
真的吗？
You don't look very Chinese to me if you don't mind me saying so.
恕我直言，你看起来不太像中国人。
It's fine.
没关系。
I am actually from Mexico.
我其实来自墨西哥。
I was in China on a business trip visiting some local companies that manufacture bathroom
我去中国出差，拜访了一些生产卫浴产品的当地公司。
products.
卫浴产品。
Wow, sounds interesting.
哇，听起来很有趣。
Excuse me if I'm being a bit nosy, but how old are you?
恕我冒昧，你多大了？
Don't you know it's rude to ask a lady her age?
你不知道问女士年龄是不礼貌的吗？
Don't get me wrong.
别误会。
It's just that you seem so young and already doing business overseas.
只是你看起来这么年轻，就已经在海外做生意了。
Well, thank you.
嗯，谢谢。
In that case, I am 26 years old.
既然这样，我26岁。
And what about yourself?
那你呢？
I'm 40 years old and was born and raised here in the good old US of A, although I have some
我40岁，出生并成长在这个美好的美利坚合众国，虽然我有一些
Colombian heritage.
哥伦比亚血统。
Really?
真的吗？
That's great.
太好了。
Do you speak Spanish?
你会说西班牙语吗？
Yeah, of course.
当然会。
¡Qué bien! Entonces podemos hablar en español.
太好了！那我们可以说西班牙语了。
Alright, so I don't think this guy spoke much Spanish, do you?
好吧，我觉得这家伙不太会说西班牙语，你觉得呢？
No, even though he has Colombian heritage, I think he doesn't speak much.
不会，尽管他有哥伦比亚血统，我觉得他不太会说。
But maybe he's just a little bit rusty.
但也许他只是有点生疏了。
Maybe.
也许吧。
But what he does speak is English.
但他确实会说英语。
And since this is EnglishPod, why don't we look at some of the phrases that they used
既然这是 EnglishPod，我们为什么不看看他们在流利度构建器中使用的
for small talk in Fluency Builder?
一些闲聊短语呢？
Fluency Builder.
流利度构建器。
Alright, so today on Fluency Builder, we're going to take a look at phrases that both
好的，今天在流利度构建器中，我们将看看乘客和出租车司机
the passenger and the taxi driver used to make small talk.
用来闲聊的短语。
So why don't we start with the first one?
那我们先从第一个开始吧？
Alright, so the taxi driver tells the passenger that she doesn't look very Chinese if you
好的，出租车司机对乘客说，恕我直言，你看起来不太像中国人。
don't mind me saying so.
恕我直言。
Right, so he said, you don't look very Chinese to me if you don't mind me saying so.
对，他说，恕我直言，你看起来不太像中国人。
If you don't mind me saying so.
恕我直言。
So what does he mean by this last part of his sentence?
那他这句话最后部分是什么意思？
Well this is a phrase that we use to soften a statement that might be a little bit rude.
这是一个用来缓和可能有点冒犯的陈述的短语。
She could be Chinese, right?
她可能是中国人，对吧？
So it may be a little bit rude to say that, but he kind of apologizes.
所以这么说可能有点冒犯，但他算是道歉了。
That's right.
没错。
By saying, if you don't mind me saying so.
通过说“恕我直言”。
Okay, so for example, I could say, hey Marco, you look a little tired today if you don't
好的，比如，我可以这样说，嘿 Marco，恕我直言，你今天看起来有点累。
mind me saying so.
恕我直言。
Okay, so does it always go at the end?
好的，这个短语总是放在句尾吗？
You could use it at the beginning.
你也可以放在句首。
If you don't mind me saying so, I just don't think this is a good idea.
恕我直言，我只是觉得这不是个好主意。
Okay, very good.
好的，非常好。
So you can use this phrase in the beginning or at the end of a sentence.
所以你可以把这个短语放在句首或句尾。
Right, and it makes your statement a little bit less rude.
对，它能让你的话不那么冒犯。
If you don't mind me saying so.
恕我直言。
Now again, he also apologizes a little bit when he says, excuse me if I am being a bit
现在，他还在说“恕我冒昧”时道歉了。
nosy, but.
恕我冒昧，但是……
Excuse me if I'm being a bit nosy, but.
Okay, so let's take a look at this.
好的，我们来看看这个。
Nosy, what's this?
冒昧，这是什么意思？
Okay, when somebody is nosy, it means they are very curious.
好的，当一个人很冒昧时，意味着他们非常好奇。
They are asking too many questions.
他们问太多问题了。
Yeah, asking more questions than they should ask.
是的，问的问题比应该问的要多。
Right, so he apologizes and says, well, excuse me if I'm asking too many questions, and then
对，所以他道歉说，嗯，恕我多问，然后
he asks her another question.
他又问了她一个问题。
He asks her how old she is.
他问她多大了。
Right, so again, it's a polite way of maybe asking a question that might be a little bit
对，所以这是一种礼貌的方式，可能问一个有点
sensitive.
敏感的问题。
Yeah, or a little bit impolite.
是的，或者有点不礼貌。
Okay, so of course, asking a woman her age maybe is a little bit impolite, right?
好的，当然，问女士年龄可能有点不礼貌，对吧？
Yes, typically women don't like that too much.
是的，通常女性不太喜欢这样。
But our next phrase, we heard the taxi driver say, don't get me wrong.
但我们的下一个短语，我们听到出租车司机说“别误会”。
Don't get me wrong.
别误会。
Okay, so don't get me wrong.
好的，别误会。
He says, well, don't misunderstand what I'm saying.
他说，嗯，别误解我的意思。
That's right.
没错。
This phrase is used so commonly in English that I think it would help us to hear some
这个短语在英语中非常常用，我觉得听一些例子
examples.
会很有帮助。
Example one.
例子一。
Don't get me wrong.
别误会。
It's not that I think you stole my computer.
我不是说你偷了我的电脑。
It's just that you were the only one who could get into my room.
只是你是唯一能进我房间的人。
Example two.
例子二。
I do have a few problems with the plan, but don't get me wrong.
我对这个计划确实有些意见，但别误会。
I still think it's a good idea.
我仍然觉得这是个好主意。
Example three.
例子三。
Don't get me wrong.
别误会。
I think John's a nice guy.
我觉得约翰是个好人。
He's just a bit disorganized.
他只是有点没条理。
All right, very good example.
好的，非常好的例子。
So don't get me wrong, right?
所以别误会，对吧？
That's right.
没错。
And now for the final phrase on putting it together today.
现在来看今天“整合”部分的最后一个短语。
Well, the passenger, the woman says her age, she says, I'm 26 years old.
嗯，乘客，那位女士说了她的年龄，她说，我26岁。
And what about yourself?
那你呢？
What about yourself?
All right.
好的。
Now, this sentence isn't very correct, actually, right?
现在，这个句子其实不太正确，对吧？
Yeah, technically, it's not correct in grammar, but it is used so commonly every day by American
是的，从语法上讲，它不正确，但在美国英语中每天都非常常用，
English speakers that we thought we'd show it to you.
所以我们想展示给你看。
Okay, so you would say, I am 26 years old and what about you?
好的，所以你会说，我26岁，你呢？
That's right.
没错。
Okay, but commonly you will hear people say, what about yourself?
好的，但你经常会听到人们说“那你呢？”
And if you use this, you'll sound really fluent and really native like.
如果你用这个，你会听起来非常流利，非常地道。
Okay, very good.
好的，非常好。
So what about yourself?
所以“那你呢？”
So again, it's just like, what about you?
所以再次强调，它就像“你呢？”
So I could say, hey, Marco, I'm going away on holiday this weekend.
所以我可以这样说，嘿 Marco，我这周末要去度假。
And what about yourself?
那你呢？
Okay, what about yourself?
好的，那你呢？
So we've taken a look at these four phrases on putting it together.
我们已经看了这四个短语在“整合”部分。
Why don't we listen to the dialogue for the second time?
我们为什么不听第二遍对话呢？
We're going to slow it down a little bit, and then we'll come back and take a look at
我们会放慢一点速度，然后回来看看语言要点中的
some vocabulary words on Language Takeaway.
一些词汇。
Where to miss?
小姐，去哪儿？
Hi, Crenshaw and Hawthorne at the Holiday Inn that is on that corner.
嗨，去那个拐角处的假日酒店，在克伦肖和霍桑街。
Sure thing.
没问题。
So where are you flying in from?
你从哪儿飞来的？
From China.
从中国。
Really?
真的吗？恕我直言，你看起来不太像中国人。
You don't look very Chinese to me, if you don't mind me saying so.
It's fine.
没关系。
I am actually from Mexico.
我其实来自墨西哥。
I was in China on a business trip, visiting some local companies that manufacture bathroom
我去中国出差，拜访了一些生产卫浴产品的当地公司。
products.
卫浴产品。
Wow, sounds interesting.
哇，听起来很有趣。
Excuse me if I'm being a bit nosy, but how old are you?
恕我冒昧，你多大了？
Don't you know it's rude to ask a lady her age?
你不知道问女士年龄是不礼貌的吗？
Don't get me wrong.
别误会。
It's just that you seem so young and already doing business overseas.
只是你看起来这么年轻，就已经在海外做生意了。
Well, thank you.
嗯，谢谢。
In that case, I am 26 years old.
既然这样，我26岁。
And what about yourself?
那你呢？
I am 40 years old and was born and raised here in the good old US of A, although I have
我40岁，出生并成长在这个美好的美利坚合众国，虽然我有一些
some Colombian heritage.
哥伦比亚血统。
Really?
真的吗？
That's great.
太好了。
Do you speak some Spanish?
你会说一些西班牙语吗？
Yeah, of course.
当然会。
¡Qué bien!
太好了！
Entonces podemos hablar en español.
那我们可以说西班牙语了。
Well, we've got some interesting vocabulary words and phrases here in Language Takeaway.
嗯，我们在语言要点中有一些有趣的词汇和短语。
And the first one...
第一个……
Well, after she gets in the taxi and tells him where she wants to go, he answers by saying
嗯，她上了出租车告诉他要去哪里后，他回答说
sure thing.
“没问题”。
Sure thing.
没问题。
So, if I say, yeah, sure thing, what does that mean?
所以，如果我说，是的，没问题，那是什么意思？
Well, let's listen to some examples to help us understand.
嗯，让我们听一些例子来帮助理解。
Example one.
例子一。
Do you mind lending me a hundred bucks?
你介意借我一百块钱吗？
Sure thing.
没问题。
Example two.
例子二。
Could you please send me the email by the end of the day?
你能在今天结束前把邮件发给我吗？
Sure thing.
没问题。
Example three.
例子三。
Do you mind lending me a hundred bucks?
你介意借我一百块钱吗？
Sure thing.
没问题。
Could you please send me the email by the end of the day?
你能在今天结束前把邮件发给我吗？
Sure thing.
没问题。
Example four.
例子四。
Can you get some milk on the way home?
你能在回家的路上买点牛奶吗？
Sure thing.
没问题。
I'm on my way now.
我正在路上。
Okay, so sure thing, basically, yeah, no problem or okay.
好的，所以“没问题”基本上就是，是的，没问题或好的。
Or I'll do it.
或者我会做的。
I'll do it.
我会做的。
It's fine.
没关系。
So, it's a very common way you will hear this a lot when somebody agrees or says yes, no
所以，这是一个非常常见的说法，当某人同意或说“是，没
problem.
问题”时，你会经常听到。
Yeah, and again, it will help you sound really native-like to use this phrase.
是的，再次强调，用这个短语会让你听起来非常地道。
Well, the next one, the taxi driver says, I was born and raised here.
嗯，下一个，出租车司机说，我在这里出生并长大。
I was born and raised here.
我在这里出生并长大。
Born and raised.
出生并长大。
Okay, so this is a way of saying I was born in this country and I haven't left this country.
好的，这是一种说法，表示我出生在这个国家，并且没有离开过这个国家。
That's right.
没错。
So, I'm from this country.
所以，我来自这个国家。
Okay.
好的。
Born and raised here in the good old US of A.
我在这里出生和长大，就在这美好的美利坚合众国。
Good old US of A. The good old US of A.
美好的美利坚合众国。美好的美利坚合众国。
So, this is a pretty interesting way of saying America.
所以，这是一种相当有趣的称呼美国的方式。
Right.
对。
It's actually more of a phrase, right?
这其实更像是一个短语，对吧？
The good old US of A. Yep.
美好的美利坚合众国。是的。
Okay.
好的。
So, it means the good United States of America.
所以，它的意思是美好的美利坚合众国。
Yeah, it's kind of a fond way or a friendly way of describing America.
是的，这是一种亲切或友好的方式来描述美国。
All right.
好的。
And we have one more word for language takeaway.
我们还有一个语言要点要讲。
Well, the taxi driver was talking about his Colombian heritage.
嗯，出租车司机在谈论他的哥伦比亚血统。
Colombian heritage.
哥伦比亚血统。
Heritage.
血统。
All right.
好的。
So, if I have Colombian heritage, what does that mean?
所以，如果我有哥伦比亚血统，那意味着什么？
Your grandmother or, you know, grandfather, great-grandmother or someone in your family
你的祖母，或者，你知道，祖父、曾祖母或你家族中的某个人
is from Colombia.
来自哥伦比亚。
Okay.
好的。
And what about the word heritage by itself?
那“血统”这个词本身是什么意思呢？
Yeah, so your heritage is basically your culture, your...
是的，你的血统基本上就是你的文化，你的……
Customs.
习俗。
Yeah, your customs, your history.
是的，你的习俗，你的历史。
Okay.
好的。
So, heritage.
所以，血统。
A country rich in heritage.
一个拥有丰富文化遗产的国家。
Lots of good old historical culture in that country.
那个国家有很多美好的历史文化。
Okay.
好的。
Very good.
非常好。
So, now it's time for us to listen to the dialogue for the last time.
所以，现在是时候让我们最后一次听对话了。
Now we can understand all these phrases and these great words that we've just looked at.
现在我们能理解所有这些短语和我们刚看过的这些好词了。
And then we'll come back and talk a little bit more.
然后我们会回来再聊一会儿。
Where to, miss?
去哪儿，小姐？
Hi.
嗨。
Crenshaw and Hawthorne at the Holiday Inn that is on that corner.
克伦肖和霍桑，在那个拐角的假日酒店。
Sure thing.
没问题。
So, where are you flying in from?
那么，你从哪儿飞来的？
From China.
来自中国。
Really?
真的吗？
You don't look very Chinese to me, if you don't mind me saying so.
你看起来不太像中国人，恕我直言。
It's fine.
没关系。
I am actually from Mexico.
我其实来自墨西哥。
I was in China on a business trip, visiting some local companies that manufacture bathroom
我当时在中国出差，拜访一些生产卫浴
products.
产品的本地公司。
Wow, sounds interesting.
哇，听起来挺有意思的。
Excuse me if I'm being a bit nosy, but how old are you?
恕我冒昧，请问你多大了？
Don't you know it's rude to ask a lady her age?
你不知道问女士年龄是不礼貌的吗？
Don't get me wrong.
别误会。
It's just that you seem so young and already doing business overseas.
只是你看起来这么年轻，就已经在海外做生意了。
Well, thank you.
嗯，谢谢。
In that case, I am 26 years old.
既然这样，我26岁。
And what about yourself?
那你呢？
I'm 40 years old and was born and raised here in the good old US of A.
我40岁，出生并成长在这美好的美利坚合众国。
Although, I have some Colombian heritage.
不过，我有一些哥伦比亚血统。
Really?
真的吗？
That's great.
那太好了。
Do you speak Spanish?
你会说西班牙语吗？
Yeah, of course.
当然会。
¡Qué bien!
太好了！
Entonces podemos hablar en español.
那我们可以说西班牙语了。
So, Marco, this taxi driver makes a bit of a mistake when he asks the woman how old
所以，Marco，这位出租车司机在问那位女士年龄时犯了个小错误。
she is.
是的，没错。
Yes, yeah, exactly.
对，确实。
There are a couple of questions that in some cultures are considered to be normal and okay,
有些问题在某些文化中被视为正常和可以接受的，
but in other cultures, they're not really well accepted.
但在其他文化中，就不太被接受。
Okay, so in Anglo culture, for example, it's really impolite to ask a woman how old she
好的，比如在盎格鲁文化中，问女士年龄是非常不礼貌的。
is.
是的。
Right.
对。
Women are a little bit more sensitive about their age.
女性对自己的年龄比较敏感。
Others aren't so much, but it's usually better to just not ask.
有些人不那么敏感，但通常最好还是别问。
Yep.
嗯。
And what else should we avoid talking about in Small Talk?
那在闲聊中，我们还应该避免谈什么？
Well, for example, when you ask a person their occupation, you can ask what they do for a
嗯，比如，当你问一个人的职业时，可以问他们做什么工作，
living, but don't ask how much money they make.
但不要问他们赚多少钱。
That's right.
没错。
Anglo people are really sensitive about talking about money.
盎格鲁人对谈论金钱非常敏感。
We hate talking about money.
我们讨厌谈钱。
Right.
对。
So, don't ask somebody their salary or how much money they make.
所以，不要问别人的薪水或他们赚多少钱。
It's just not considered to be polite.
这被认为是不礼貌的。
And another good one to be careful of is asking if someone is married or not.
另一个要小心的问题是问别人是否结婚了。
Right.
对。
Sometimes you're just being friendly and you want to know if that person has family or
有时候你只是想友好一点，想知道那个人有没有家人或
something, but you have to be careful when and where you ask this question.
什么，但你必须注意在什么时候和什么地方问这个问题。
Right.
对。
If they've mentioned their family, if they've talked about their kids or something else
如果他们提到了自己的家人，谈到了孩子或其他
to do with their family, then it's okay.
与家庭有关的事情，那就没问题。
Right.
对。
You can say, well, oh, how long have you been married?
你可以说，哦，你结婚多久了？
Yeah.
是的。
But if a guy asks a girl, oh, are you married?
但如果一个男人问一个女人，哦，你结婚了吗？
It kind of sounds like maybe he's interested in her or that he's trying to come on to
这听起来有点像他可能对她感兴趣，或者他在试图
her and to be maybe more than friendly, right?
搭讪，可能不只是友好，对吧？
That's right.
没错。
Okay.
好的。
So, some great Small Talk tips and phrases here at EnglishPod.
所以，在EnglishPod这里有一些很好的闲聊技巧和短语。
Now, if you have any questions about this lesson or any other lessons, be sure to visit
现在，如果你对本课或其他任何课程有疑问，一定要访问
our website at EnglishPod.com.
我们的网站EnglishPod.com。
And if you also have any doubts about which questions you think are appropriate of asking
如果你对哪些问题适合问别人还有疑问，
somebody, yeah, come into the website and let us know.
是的，来网站告诉我们。
So, thanks for downloading, you guys.
所以，感谢你们的下载。
And until next time, goodbye.
下次再见，拜拜。